Okay, this lecture is like the beginning
of the second half of this course
because up to now we paid a lot of
attention to rectangular
matrices.
Now concentrating on square matrices. So
we've got two big topics. the
determinant of a square matrix. So this
is the first lecture in that new chapter
on determinants and the reason the big
reason we need the determinants is for
the igen values. So this is really
determinants and igen values the next
big big chunk of
1806. Okay. So the determinant is a
number associated with every square
matrix. So every square matrix has this
number associated with it called its
determinant. Uh I'll I'll often write it
as
deta or often also I'll write it as
uh a with vertical bars. So that's going
to mean the determinant of the matrix.
That's going to mean this one like magic
number. Well, one number can't tell
you what the whole matrix
was, but this one number just packs in
as much information as possible into a
single number. And of course the one
fact that you've seen before and we have
to see it again
is the matrix is invertible when the
determinant is not zero. The matrix is
singular when the determinant is zero.
So that's the determinant will be a test
for
invertability. But the determin's got a
lot more to it than that. So let me
start. Okay. Now the question is how to
start. Do I give you a big formula for
the determinant all in one gulp? I don't
think so. That big formula has got too
much packed in it. I would
rather start with
three properties of the determinant.
Three three properties that it has. And
and let me tell you property one. The
determinant of the identity is one.
Okay, I I wish the other two properties
were as easy to tell you as that. But
actually the second property is pretty
straightforward too. And then once we
get the
third, we will actually have the
determinant. Those three properties
define the determinant and we can then
we can figure out well what is the
determinant? What's a formula for it?
Okay, can I tell you the second
property? This that just like scales the
determinant so that the identity matrix
has determinant one. Now the second
property is what happens if you exchange
two rows of a matrix? What happens to
the determinant? So, so property two is
exchange
rows. Reverse the
sign of the
determinant. A lot of plus and minus
signs. I even wrote here plus and minus
signs because this is like that's what
you have to pay attention to in the
formulas and properties of determinants.
So
that you see what I mean by a property
here. I I I'm I haven't yet told you
what the determinant is but whatever it
is if I exchange two rows to get a
different
matrix that reverses the sign of the
determinant. And so now
actually what matrices do we now know
the determinant of from from one and
two I now know the determinant well I
certainly know the determinant of the
identity matrix and now I know the
determinant of every other matrix that
comes from row
exchanges from the identity still. So
what matrices have I got at this
point? the permutations. Right? At this
point, I know every permutation matrix.
So now I'm saying the determinant of a
permutation matrix is one or minus
one. One or minus one depending whether
the number of exchanges was
even or the number of exchanges was odd.
So this is the determinant of a
permutation. Now P is back to standing
for
permutation. Okay. So if if I I could
carry on this board, I could like do the
2x twos. So property one tells me that
this 2x two matrix Oh, I better write
absolute I mean I better write vertical
bars not brackets for that
determinant. Property one said in the 2x
two case that this matrix has
determinant
one. Property two tells me that this
matrix has
determinant what negative
1. This is like 2x two. And now I
finally want to get well ultimately I
want to get to a the formula that we all
know.
Let me put that way over here. That the
determinant of a general 2x two
is a d minus b c.
Okay, I I I'm going to leave that up
like as one as as the 2 by two case that
we already know so that every
property I can like check that it's
correct for 2 by
twos. But the whole point of these
properties is that they're going to give
me a formula for n byn. That's the whole
point. they're going to give me this
number that that's a test for
invertability and other great properties
for any size matrix. Okay, now you see
I'm
like slowing down because property three
is the key property. Property three is
the key property. And can I somehow
describe it? Maybe I'll separate it into
3 A and 3B.
Property 3A says that if I have that if
I multiply one of the rows, say the
first
row
by a number
T. I'm going to erase that. That that
that's like what I'm headed for, but I'm
not there yet. Uh that's the one we
know. and you'll see that it's checked
out by by each uh
property. Okay. Now, what's so this is
for any
matrix? For any matrix, if I multiply
one row by T and leave the other row or
or other N minus one rows alone, what
happens to the
determinant? The factor T comes
out. It's T times this determinant.
That's not hard. I shouldn't have made a
big deal out of property 3A. And 3B is
that if is is if I keep I'm always
keeping this second row the same or the
last n minus one rows are all staying
the same. I'm just working I'm just
looking inside the first row. And if I
have an a plus a prime there and a b + b
prime
there. Sorry, I didn't ah why don't I'll
use an eraser to do it right. B + B
prime there. Do you see what I'm doing?
This property and this property are
about linear
combinations of the first row only
leaving the other rows unchanged. They
they'll they'll copy along.
Then then I get the sum this breaks up
into the sum of this
determinant and this one.
If I'm putting up formulas, maybe I can
try to say it in words. The determinant
is a linear
function. It it behaves like a a linear
function of the first
row if all the other rows stay the same.
I am not saying that the I am let me
emphasize I am not saying that the
determinant of a plus b
is determinant of
A plus determinant of B. I am not saying
that. I better Can I How do I get it
onto tape that I'm not saying that? You
see, this would allow
uh all the rows, you know, A to have a
bunch of rows, B to have a bunch of
rows. That's not the linearity I'm
after. I'm only after linearity in each
row.
Linear for each
row. Well, you may say I only talked
about the first row, but I claim it's
also linear in the second row. If I had
this, but not I can't I can't have a
combination in both first and second
row. If I had a combination in the
second row, then I could use rule two to
put it up in the first row, use my use
my property and then use rule two again
to put it back.
So each row is okay, not only the first
row but each row
separately. Okay, those are the three
properties. And from those properties,
so that's properties one, two, three.
from
those I want to get all I want to learn
a lot more about the
determinant let me take an example what
what would I like to learn I would like
to learn that so here's a property four
let me use the same numbering as here
property
four is if two rows are equal
the determinant
is zero. Okay. So, property
four, two equal
rows lead to
determinant equals
zero. Right?
Now of course I can in the 2x two case I
can check sure the determinant of
ab comes out zero
but I want to see why it's true for n
byn suppose row one equals row 3 for a 7
by7
matrix so two rows are the same in a big
matrix and all I have to work with is
these
properties the exchange property which
flips the sign and the linearity
property which is works in each row
separately.
Okay, can you see the reason? How do I
how do I get this one out of properties
one two three because that's all I have
to work with. Everything has to come
from properties one two three. Okay. So
suppose I have a matrix and two rows are
equal. How do I see that its determinant
has to be
zero from these
properties? I do an
exchange. Property two is just set up
for this. Use property two. Use exchange
exchange
rows. exchange those
rows and I get the same
matrix of course because those rows were
equal so the determinant didn't change
but on the other hand property two says
that the sign did change so the so I I
have a determinant whose sign doesn't
change and does change and the only
possibility ility then is that the
determinant is zero. You see the
reasoning there? Straightforward
property two just told us, hey, if we've
got two equal
rows, we we've got
um a zero determinant. And of course in
our minds that matches the fact that if
I have two equal rows, the matrix isn't
invertible. If I have two equal rows, I
know that the rank is less than n. Okay,
ready for property
five? Now, property five you'll
recognize
as a
key. It says
that the elimination step that I'm
always doing.
Subtract a
multiple subtract some multiple L times
row one from
another row
row k let's
say you remember why I did that that in
elimination I'm I'm always choosing this
multiplier so as to produce
zero in that in that
position or or row i from row k maybe I
should just make very clear that there's
nothing special about row one
here. Okay. So that you can see why I
want that one because that will allow me
to start with this full matrix whose
determinant I don't know and I can do
elimination and clean it out. I can get
zeros below the diagonal by these
elimination steps. And the point is that
the that the
determinant the
determinant doesn't
change. So all those steps of
elimination are are okay not changing
the determinant in our in our language
in in the early chapter. The determinant
of a is going to be the same as the
determinant of u, the upper triangular
one that just has the pivots on the
diagonal. That's why we'll want this
property. Okay, do you see where that
property is coming
from? Let let me do the 2x two case. Let
me do the 2 x two case here. So, uh I'll
I'll keep property five going along. So,
what am I doing? I'm going to keep I'm
going to have
AB CD, but I'm going to subtract L times
the first row from the second
row. And that's the
determinant. And of course, I can
multiply that out and figure out sure
enough a D minus BC is there. And this
minus ALB plus A alb cancels out. But I
just cheated, right? I've got to use the
property. So what property? Well, of
course, this is a com. I'm keeping the
first row the same. And the second row
has a C and a D. And then there's the
determinant of the A and the B and the
minus L A and the minus LB.
So what property was
that?
3B. I kept one row the same and I had a
combination in the second in the other
row and I just separated it
out. Okay. So that's property three.
This is by number three. 3B if you like.
Okay. Now use 3A. How how do you use
3A, which says I can factor out an L? I
can factor out a minus L here. I can
factor a minus L out from this row. No
problem. That was
3A. So now I've used property three. And
now I'm ready for the
kill. Property four says that this
determinant
is zero, has two equal rows.
Do you see how that would always work? I
subtract off a multiple of one row from
another one. It gives me a combination
in row K of the old
row and L times this copy of a higher
row. And then if I since I have two
equal rows, that's zero. So the
determinant after elimination is the
same as before. Good. Okay. Now let's
see if I rescue my glasses I can see
what's property six. Oh six is easy pl
of space
row of
zeros leads to determinant of a equals
zero a complete row of zeros. So I'm I'm
again this is like
uh something that I'll use in the
singular case. Actually you can you can
look ahead to why I need these
properties. So I'm going to use property
five the elimination use this stuff to
say that this determinant is the same as
that determinant and I'll produce a zero
there. But what if I also produce a zero
there? What if elimination gives a row
of zeros? Then I that that used to be my
test for
singular not invertible rank two rank
less than n and now I'm seeing it's also
gives determinant zero. Uh how do I get
that
one from the previous properties because
I this is not a new law this has got to
come from the old
one. So what what shall I do? 3. Yeah,
use that's brilliant. Use 3A with T
equals Z. Right. So I have this I have
this Z 0 CD and I'm trying to show that
that determinant is
zero. Okay. So but zero is the same as
five. Can I take T equal 5 just to like
pin it down? I'll multiply this row by
five. Five. Well then five of this
should if I if there's a factor
five in
that you see
what so this is property 3 a with with
taking as five if I multiply a row by
five outcomes a five so why am I why the
heck am I doing
this oh
because that's still 0 0
So that's this determinant equals 5 *
this
determinant
and the determinant has to be zero. I I
think I I didn't do that the very best
way. You were Yeah, you had the idea
better. Multiply. Yeah. Yeah. Take T
equals Z. Was that your idea? Yeah.
Better. Take T equals Z. in rule 3B. If
T is zero in rule 3B, can I bring the
camera back to rule 3B?
Sorry. If if T is
zero, then I have a Z 0 there and the
determinant is zero. Okay? One way or
another, a row of zeros mean zero
determinant.
Okay? Now I have to get serious.
the the next properties are the ones
that we we're building up to.
Okay, so I can do
elimination. I can reduce to a
triangular
matrix. And now what's the determinant
of that triangular matrix? Suppose
suppose I all right rule
seven. So suppose my matrix is now
triangular. So it's
got so I even give these the names of
the pivots D1 D2 to DN and stuff is up
here. I don't know what that
is. But what I do know is this is all
zero. That's all
zero. And I would like to know the
determinant because elimination will get
me to this. So once I'm here, what's the
determinant? Let me use an eraser to get
those get that vertical bar again. So
that I'm taking the determinant of u so
that so what is the
determinant of an upper triangular
matrix? Do you know the
answer? It's just the product of the
D's.
the these things that I don't even put
in letters for because they don't
matter. The determinant is d1 * d2
*
dn. If I have a triangular
matrix, then the diagonal is all I have
to look at.
And that's that's telling us then we now
have the way that mat
lab any reasonable software would
compute a determinant. If I have a a
matrix of size
100 the way I would actually compute its
determinant would be
elimination make it triangular multiply
the pivots together the product of the
pivots. product of
pivots. Now, there's
always in
determinance a plus or a minus sign to
remember. Where does that come in to
this
rule? Could it be could the determinant
be minus the product of the
pivots? The determinant is d1 d2 to dn.
No doubt about that. But to get to this
triangular form, we may have had to do a
row exchange. So,
so this it's the product of the pivots.
If there were no row exchanges, if if
SLU code, the simple LU code, just
square LU went right through. If we had
to do some row exchanges, then we've got
to watch plus or minus. Okay, but the
this law is simply that. Okay, how do I
prove
that? Let's see. Let me suppose that
these are not
zero. The pivots are not
zero. And tell me how do I show that
none of this upper stuff makes any
difference? How do I get zeros
there? By elimination. Right? I just
multiply this row by the right number,
subtract from that row, kills
that. I multiply this row by the right
number, kills that. By the right number,
kills that. I can kill every one of
these off diagonal terms, no problem.
And I'm just left with the
diagonal. Well, strictly speaking, I
still have to figure out why is for a
diagonal matrix. Now why is that the
right
determinant? I mean we sure hope it is
but why I have to go back to properties
1 2
3. Why is now that the matrix is
suddenly
diagonal? How do I know that the
determinant is just a product of those
diagonal entries? Well, what am I going
to use? I'm going to use property 3A. Is
that right? I'll I'll I'll factor this
I'll factor this I'll factor that D1 out
and have one and have the first row will
be that and then I'll factor out the D2.
Should I can I put the D2 here and the
second row will look like that and so
on. So I factored out all the D's and
what am I left with? The identity. And
what rule do I finally get to use?
rule one finally this is the point where
rule one finally chips in and says that
that determinant is one so it's the
product of the D's. So this was rules
rules five to do
elimination 3 a to factor out the d's
and and our best friend rule one and
possibly rule two the exchanges may have
been needed also.
Okay, now I guess I have to consider
also the case if some D is
zero because I was assuming I could use
the D's to clean out and make it
diagonal. But what if what if one of
those diagonal entries is zero? Well,
then with elimination, we know that we
can get a row of zeros.
And for a row of zeros, I'm using rule
six. The determinant is zero. And that's
right. So, so I can check the singular
case. In fact, I can now get to the key
point that determinant of
a is zero exactly when exactly
when a is
single and otherwise it's not zero. So
that the determinant is a fair test for
invertability or
non-invertability. Okay. So I must be
close to that because I can take any
matrix and get there. Do I did I have
anything to
say? The the proof that starts by saying
by elimination go from A to U. Oh yeah.
actually looks to me like I don't
haven't said anything brand new
here that that really I've got
this because let's just remember the
reasoning by elimination I can go
from the original A to
U. Well, okay. Now suppose the matrix is
is is singular. Okay. If the matrix is
singular, what what happens? Then by
elimination, I get a row of
zeros and therefore the determinant is
zero. And if the matrix is not singular,
I don't get zero. So maybe do you want
me to put this like in two parts? The
determinant of a is not zero
when a is inverted.
because I I've
already in chapter two we figured out
when is the matrix invertible. It's
invertible when elimination produces a
full set of pivots and now and we now we
know the determinant is the product of
those nonzero numbers. So those are the
two cases the if it's singular I go to a
row of
zeros. If it's invertible I go to u and
then to the diagonal d and then which
and then to d1 d2 up to
dn as the formula. So we we have a
formula
now. We have a formula for the
determinant and it's actually a very
much more practical formula than the AD
minus BC
formula. Is it correct? I maybe should
just let's just check that 2x two. What
are the pivots of a 2x two
matrix? What what does elimination do
with that 2x2 matrix?
it. There's the first pivot. Fine.
What's the second
pivot? We subtract. So, so, so I'm
putting it in its upper triangular form.
What do I, my multiplier
is C over A, right? I multiply that row
by C / A and I subtract to get that
zero. And here I have D minus C / A time
B.
That's the elimination on a 2x two.
So I've finally discovered that the
determinant of this matrix I' I've just
I've got it from the properties not by
knowing the answer from last
year that the determinant of this 2x two
is the product of a times that and of
course when I multiply a by that the
product of that and that is a d minus
the a's cancel bc
So that's great provided A isn't
zero. If A was zero, that step wasn't
allowed. Zero wasn't a pivot. So that's
what
I've I've covered all the bases. I have
to if if A is zero, then I have to do
the
exchange. And if the exchange doesn't
work, it's because A is singular.
Okay, those are
[Music]
the those are the direct properties of
the
determinant. And now finally, I've got
two more nine and 10.
And
that's I I think you can like
uh the ones we've got
here are so are are totally connected
with our elimination
process and and what whether pivots are
available and whether or whether we get
a row of zeros. I think all that you can
swallow in one shot. Let me tell you
properties nine and
10. They're quick to write
down. They're very, very
useful. So, I'll just write them down
and use them. Property nine says that
the determinant of a product if I
multiply two
matrices. So if I multiply two matrices
A and
B that the determinant of the product
is determinant of
A times determinant of
B. And for me that one is
like that's a very valuable property and
it's sort of like partly coming out of
the blue because we haven't been
multiplying matrices. And here suddenly
this
determinant has this multiplying
property. Remember it didn't have the
linear property. It didn't have the
adding property. The determinant of a
plus b is not the sum of the determinant
but the determinant of a times b is the
product of it is the product of it.
Okay. So for
example, what's the determinant of a
inverse using that property
nine? Let me let me put that under here
because the camera is happier if it can
focus on both at once. So let me put it
underneath. The determinant of a inverse
because I I won't and the property 10
will come
uh in that
space. What what does this tell me about
a inverse its determinant? Okay. Well,
what do I know about a
inverse? I know that a inverse time a is
odd. So, what am I going to do?
I'm going to take determinants of both
sides. The determinant of I is one and
what's the determinant of A inverse
A? That's a product of two matrices A
and B. So it's the product of the
determinant. So what am I learning? I'm
learning that the determinant of A
inverse times the determinant of
A is the determinant of I. That's this
one. Again, I happily use property one.
Okay. So, that tells me that the
determinant of a inverse is one over
here's my here's my conclusion is one
over the determinant of
a. I guess that that I I always try to
think well do we know some cases of
that? Of course we know it's right
already if a is diagonal. If a is a
diagonal
matrix then it's determined as just a
product of those numbers. So if if a is
for example 2
3 then we know that a inverse is 12
1/3 and sure enough that has
determinant six and that has determinant
16 and our rule
checks. So somehow this proof this
property has to somehow the proof of of
that property if we can boil it down to
diagonal matrices then we can read it
off whether it's A and A inverse or two
different diagonal matrices A and B for
diagonal. So what am I saying? I'm
saying for diagonal matrices,
check. But we'd have to do elimination
steps. We'd have to patiently do the the
uh argument if we want to use these
previous properties to get it for other
matrices. It it also tells me what just
let's see what else it's telling me.
What's the determinant of of a squ? If I
take a matrix and square
it, then the determinant just got
squared, right? The determinant of a
squared is the determinant of a time the
determinant of a. So if I square the
matrix, I square the determinant. If I
double the
matrix, what do I do to the
determinant? Think about that. If I
double the matrix, So the determinant of
a so I'm writing down like facts that
follow the determinant of a
squared is the determinant of a all
squared the determinant of 2
a is
what that's a +
a but wait there I I don't want the
answer to determinant of A here that's
wrong. It's not two determinant of A.
What is it? What's what's the number
that I have to multiply determinant of A
by? If I if I double the whole matrix.
If I double every entry in the matrix,
what happens to the
determinant? It suppose it's an N byN
matrix. 2 to the N, right? Two to the
nth. Now, why is it 2 to the nth and not
just
two? So, why is it 2 to the
nth? Because I'm factoring out two from
every row. There's a factor, this has a
factor two in every row. So, I can
factor two out of the first row. I
factor a different two out of the second
row, a different two out of the nth row.
So, I've got all those twos coming out.
So, it's it's It's like volume really.
And that's the that's one of the great
applications of determinant. If I if if
if I have a
box and I double all the
sides, I multiply the volume by 2 to the
n. If it's a box in three dimensions,
I've multiplied the volume by
8. And that's so that's this is rule 3A
here. This is rule
nine. And notice the way this rule sort
of checks out with a singular non-s
singular
stuff.
That that if a is
invertible, what does that mean about
its determinant? It's not zero. And
therefore, this makes sense.
the case when determinant of a is zero.
That's the case where my
formula doesn't work anymore. If
determinant of a is zero, this is this
is ridiculous. And that's ridiculous. A
inverse doesn't
exist. And one over zero doesn't make
sense. Okay,
so don't miss this property. It's sort
of like amazing that it can. And the
10th
property
is equally simple to state that the
determinant of a transpose equals the
determinant of
a. And of course, let's just check it on
the AB CD
guy. We could check that. Sure enough,
that's AB CD. It works.
It's a d minus bc. It's a d minus bc.
Sure enough. So that that transposing
did not change the
determinant. But what it does change is
uh well what it what it does is it lists
so all I've been working with
rows. If a if a row is all zeros the
determinant is zero. But now with rule
10, I know what to do. If a column is
all zero, if a column is all zero,
what's the
determinant? Zero again. So like all
those properties about rows, exchanging
two rows reverses the sign. Now
exchanging two columns reverses the sign
because I can always if I want to see
why I can transpose those columns become
rows. I do the exchange I transpose back
and I've done a column operation.
So in in in conclusion, there was
nothing special about row one because I
could exchange rows. And now there's
nothing special about rows that that
isn't equally true for columns because
this is the same. Okay. And again, maybe
I
won't Oh, let's see. Do we maybe it's
worth seeing a quick proof of this
number 10? A quick a quick uh proof of
number
10. Let me take the this is number
10. A
transpose equals
a determinant of a transpose equals
determinant of a. That's what I should
have said. Okay. So let let's just uh
um
let a typical matrix A if I use
elimination is factors into
LU and the transpose
is U transpose
LRPOSE. This
is let me this is to prove
So this is this is prove this is prove
number
using well I don't know which ones I'll
use so I'll put them all in one to nine.
Okay I'm going to prove number 10 by
using one to nine. I won't cover every
case but I'll cover almost every case.
So in almost every case a can factor
into lu and arpose can factor into that.
Now what do I do next? So I want to
prove that these are the
same. I see a product
here. So I use rule
nine. So now what I want to prove is so
I now I know that this is L u this is U
transpose and
LRPOS. Now just for practice what are
all those determinants?
So this is this is this is prove this
prove this prove this and now I'm ready
to do
it. What's the determinant of
L? You remember what L is? It's this
lower triangular matrix with ones on the
diagonal. So what is the determinant of
that guy? It's
one. Anytime I have this triangular
matrix, I can get rid of all the
nonzeros down to the diagonal case. The
determinant of L is one. How about the
determinant of L
transpose? That's triangular also,
right? Still got those ones on the
diagonal. It's just the
nonzeros flip to the other side of the
diagonal, but they didn't matter anyway.
That's my proof really that once I've
got triangular matrices L and L
transpose or U and U transpose when
they're triangular I'm down to the
product of the diagonal and if I
transpose who
cares okay
so that's not I didn't put in
every comma and and cross every E in
that proof. But that's really the proof.
That's the like concrete proof that
that get get down to triangular matrices
and then get down to diagonal matrices.
Okay, one more comment which I I have to
make because all math professors
watching this
will be waiting for it. Okay, so they
had to wait until the last minute.
What I way way back in property two I
said that if you do a row exchange the
determinant changes sign. So if I do
seven row exchanges the determinant
changes sign. But it would it be
possible to to produce the same matrix
with seven row exchanges and with 10 row
exchanges. If that were
possible, that would be a bad thing,
right? If I could, why would it be bad?
My whole lecture would die, right?
Because rule two said that if you do
seven row
exchanges, then the sign of the
determinant reverses. But if you do 10
row exchanges, the sign of the
determinant stays the same because minus
one 10 times is + one. Okay?
So there's a hidden fact here that
every like every permutation the
permutations are either odd or
even I could get the permutation with
seven row exchanges then I could
probably get it with 21 or 23 or
101 if it's an odd one or an even number
of permutations. So, but that's the key
fact that this takes another little
algebraic trick to see. And that means
that the determinant is well defined by
properties 1 2 3 and it's got properties
4 to 10. Okay, that's today and I'll try
to get the homework for next Wednesday
onto the web.
Thank you for coming.